Guide to the Norman Foerster Papers, 1918-1940
Department of Special Collections
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - W.S. Knickerbocker to NF ( 29 Oct 1929; 9 Dec 1929; 6 Jan 1930; 20 Jan 1930; 26 Feb 1930; 5 Mar 1930; 10 Mar 1930; 11 Apr 1930; 2 May 1930; 30 Sep 1930)., 10 letters:
  - NF to W.S. Knickerbocker ( 14 Sep 1929; 3 Mar 1930; 30 Apr 1930)., 3 letters:
  - E.C. Aswell to NF ( 28 Jun 1928; 5 Apr 1929; 8 Apr 1929; 6 Jun 1929; 12 Jun 1929; 3 Sep 1929; 3 Sep (1929?); 12 Sep 1929; 23 Sep 1929)., 9 letters:
  - NF to E.C. Aswell ( 27 Mar 1929; 19 Apr 1929; 27 May 1929; 8 Jun 1929; 6 Sep 1929; 16 Sep 1929; 25 Sep 1929)., 8 letters:
  - S. Collins to NF ( 24 Nov 1929; 11 Dec 1929; 6 Jan 1930; 19 Feb 1930; 8 Mar 1930)., 5 letters:
  - S. Collins to G.R. Elliott ( N.D.), 1 letter, page #2
  - NF to S. Collins ( 29 Nov 1929; 30 Nov 1929; 16 Dec 1929; 27 Dec 1929; 9 Jan 1930., 5 letters:
  - #William S. Knickerbocker (ed. of The Sewanee Review) to NF, March 5, 1930.Great danger in Babbitt's type of humanism: that it diverts reflection from literature to the maintenance of a philosophical system mostly exhibitied negatively through fierce onslaughts on the unrecognizable. Man is educable animal (over and above being trainable).
  - #W.S. Knickerbocker to NF, Mar 10, 1930.
    Doubts wisdom of NF's relentless pursuit of logic and destructions. Repeats refusal to expose publicly his def. of humanism. W.S.K. calls himself creative humanist as distinguished from restrictive humanist (Babbitt...).
  - #NF to Knickerbocker, Dec 14, 1929.
    Ever since came under spell of Babbitt in 1910, conscious task to work free of the formalism of a disciple. Purpose should be clarification of standards rather than history of humanism.
  - #NF to Edward C. Aswell (ass. ed. of The Forum) March 27 1929,solicitation for contribution to the symposium.
  - #NF to Aswell, Sept 25, 1929.
    Reply to Aswell's withdrawal as contributor.
  - Seward Collins to NF (ed. The Bookman) Nov 24, 1929Has decided best way for Bookman to advance the humanist cause is not by becoming a partyorgan but having predominantly humanist tone yet maintain sizable audience because of the other material run. Tells of a Knickerbocker letter (confidential) telling him that Babbitt, More and NF are not such sound scholars as he thinks.
  - #Collins to NF, Dec 11, 1929,wants to goad nonhumanists into open hostility (over the symposium), thus bringing about a re-alignment.
  - #NF to Collins, Nov 29, 1929,difficulty of humanists to fill the sapce of the Bookman.
  - #Aswell to NF, April 5, 1929, Forum not yet ready to publish type of article that NF had enclosed.
  - #Aswell to NF, Sept 23, 1929,reveals that will be unable to contribute to symposium after all.
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - S.B. Gass to NF ( 9 Apr 1929; 25 Aug 1929; 30 Nov. 1929), 3 letters:
  - NF to S.B. Gass ( 28 Mar 1929; 20 Apr 1929 31 Aug 1929; 16 Oct 1929)., 4 letters:
  - NF to R. Shafer ( 31 Aug 1929)., 1 letter:
  - S.R. Gair to NF (5 Sep 1929)., 1 letter:
  - NF to S.R. Gair ( 29 Aug 1929; 10 Sep 1929), 2 letters:
  - P.H. Houston to NF ( 10 Nov 1923; 29 Nov 1923; 5 Jan 1924; 22 May 1927; 11 Jun 1928; 11 Jul 1928; 12 Aug 1928; 19 Sep 1928; 20 Jan 1929; 28 Jan 1929; 1 Feb 1929; 22 Feb 1929; 26 Feb 1929; 9 Mar 1929; 28 Mar 1929; 16 Jul 1929; 23 Sep 1929; 26 Oct 1929)., 18 letters:
  - P.H. Houston to Irving Babbitt ( 7 Jul 1927), extract, copy in NF's hand)
  - G.R. Elliott to NF ( 23 Feb 1929), 1 letter:
  - R. Shafer to NF ( 7 Mar 1929), 1 letter:
  - NF to P.H. Houston ( 18 Nov 1923; 11 May 1927; 26 Jun 1928; 14 Jul 1928; 20 Aug 1928; 7 Jan 1929; 9 Feb 1929; 15 Feb 1929; 1 Mar 1929; 12 Mar 1929; 16 Mar 1929; 20 Apr 1929; 19 Sep 1929; 14 Oct 1929; 16 Aug 1930), 15 letters:
  - G.R. Elliott to NF (ca. 1927 (?): 11 Nov 1927; 5 Jan 1928; 7 Sep 1928; 24 Sep 1928; 21 Dec 1928; 24 Dec 1928; 19 Feb 1929; 24 Mar 1929; 11 Apr 1929; 29 Jan 1929; 8 May 1929; 15 Jul 1929; 27 Aug 1929; 9 Sep 1929; 10 Sept 1929; 14 Sep 1929; 6 Oct 1929; 13 Oct 1929; 29 Oct 1929; 3 Nov 1929; 25 Nov 1929; 2 Dec 1929; 3 Dec 1929 (telegram); 4 Dec 1929; 23 Feb 1930; 8 Jun 1929; 25 Sep 1929; 19 Aug 1930; 11 Mar 1931; 22 Apr 1931)., 31 letters:
  - G.R. Elliott to S. Collins (11 Dec 1929), 1 letter:
  - NF to G.R. Elliott (20 Oct 1927; 21 Jan 1928; 18 Jun 1928; 27 Jun 1928; 22 Aug 1928; 21 Sep 1928; 26 Sep 1928; 27 Dec 1928; 15 Feb 1929; 18 Feb 1929; 2 Apr 1929; 18 Apr 1929; 5 Sep 1929; 17 Sep 1929; 19 Sep 1929; 2 Oct 1929; 15 Feb 1930; 28 Jul 1930; 7 Mar 1931; 19 Apr 1931; 25 Apr 1931; 29 May 1931)., 22 letters:
  - #Sidney R. Gair, Sep 5 1929,complains of the harshness of Babbitt & More.
  - #NF to G.R. Elliott, Oct 20, 1927,speculations on which of the two should be editor.
  - #NF to G.R. Elliott, Sep 17, 1929,comments on contributions to H.& A., defeat is its difficult style.
  - #NF to G.R. Elliott, Sep 19, 1929,comments on Lippmann's humanism.
    #REcommendation of G.R. Elliott by NF for position in English dept. (Chapel Hill?).
  - #NF to Elliott, Apr 25, 1931,mainly because of high salary Elliott cannot secure position at Chapel Hill (?).
  - #G.R. Elliott to NF, Nov 11, 1927,Elliott refuses to edit symposium.
  - #Elliott to NF May 8, 1929,dispute between Babbitt & More on morality from grace or incarnation.
  - #Elliott to NF, Aug 27, 1929,on T.S. Elliot's contribution--agrees with 51 percent--would improve upon by saying what means by humanism is balance.
  - #Elliott to NF, Nov 25, 1929,suggests bibliography of critical works in symposium--would desarm reviewers.
  - #Elliott to NF, Dec 4, 1929,extremely critical of Spring's essay (Again G.R. Elliott very fearful of what reviewers will do to essay.
  - #Shafer to Elliott, March 7, 1929(letter in wrong section?)
  - #Percy H. Houston to NF, Nov 10, 1923(Univ. of Cal. Southern Branch, L.A.) seems to originate idea of the symposium.
  - # P.H. Houston to NF, March 9, 1929(Occidental College) thing for Humanists to fear.
  - #Houston NF, Oct 26, 1929,Houston can't contribute (first effort had been severly criticised.)
  - #Sherlock B. Gass, Apr 19, 1929,two minds should think same thought even for some other formula.
    (Note: Gass sends 2 essays for NF to choose from for symposium).
  - #NF to Houston, May 11, 1927,development of idea of symposium.
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - R. Shafer to NF (6 Jan 1927; 28 Jun 1928; 30 Aug 1928; 17 Sep 1928; 26 Oct 1928; 28 Nov 1928; 20 Jan 1929; 25 Jan 1929; 11 Feb 1929; 20 Mar 1929; 8 Apr 1929; 3 May 1929; 19 Jul 1929; 25 Aug 1929; 5 Sep 1929; 16 Sep 1929; 18 Sep 1929; 24 Sep 1929; 29 Sep 1929; 3 Oct 1929; 8 Oct 1929; 28 Oct 1929; 11 Nov 1929; 25 Nov 1929; 29 Nov 1929; 6 Dec 1929; 7 Dec 1929; 11 Jan 1930; 10 Feb 1930; 23 Apr 1930; 25 Sep 1930; 1 Oct 1930)., 33 letters:
  - NF to R. Shafer 30 Jan 1928; 27 Jun 1928; 1 Aug 1928; 17 Aug 1928; 25 Sep 1928; 15 Nov 1928; 4 Dec 1928; 4 Dec 1928; 23 Jan 1929; 6 Feb 1929; 28 Mar 1929; 20 Apr 1929; 7 May 1929; 24 Jul 1929; 29 Aug 1929; 21 Sep 1929; 1 Oct 1929; 2 Nov 1929; 2 Dec 1929; 6 Jan 1930; 13 Aug 1930; 28 Sep 1930)., (21 letters:
  - #N.F. to R. Shafer, March 28, 1924;remarks that Shafer only one objecting to inclusion of Babbitt & More.
  - #NF to R. Shafer, Nov 2, 1929;More has developed religious bent more than his humanism.
  - #Shafer to NF, June 28, 1928;symposium best if chiefly gave examples of what new humanism practically means in contact with current ideas of their literary expression.
  - #Shafer to NF, Aug 25, 1929;answers questionaire about what & who made him a humanist. (Questions not actually given.)
  - #Shafer to NF, Sep 16, 1929;criticism of T.S. Eliot and B. Bandler's papers.
  - #Shafer to NF, N v 29, 1929;reports of Collins' extreme criticism of Spring's article.
  - #Shafer to NF, Dec 6, 1929;agrees with Collins that Spring's article whould be deleted. Spring is humanitarian rather than humanist, but doesn't know the difference.
- Correspondence: (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - S.P. Chase to NF 10 Oct 1928; 17 Dec 1928; 1 Jul 1929; 8 Jul 1929; 3 Sep 1929; 23 Sep 1929; 26 Sep 1929; 29 Sep 1929; 2 Oct 1929; 21 Oct 1929; 28 Nov 1929; 5 Jan 1930; 8 Jan 1930)., (13 letters:
  - NF to S.P. Chase 6 Aug 1928; 10 Aug 1928; 17 Oct 1928; 26 Dec 1928; 5 Sep 1929; 24 Sep 1929; 7 Dec 1929; 1 Jan 1930)., (8 letters:
  - G.R. Elliott to NF copy of GRE to SPC 15 Oct 1928)., (1 letter:
  - R.L. Brown to NF 26 Nov 1929), (1 letter:
  - B.Bandler to NF 18 Mar 1929; 4 Apr 1929 30 Apr 1929; 27 Aug 1929; 3 Sep 1929; 18 Sep 1929; [9 23 Sep 1929; 3 Oct 1929; 5 Oct 1929 (telegram); 15 Nov 1929)., (10 letters:
  - NF to B. Bandler 29 Mar 1929; 10 Apr 1929; 24 May 1929; 29 Aug 1929; 20 Sep 1929; 14 Oct 1929; 29 Apr 1930)., (7 letters:
  - J. Farrar to B. Bandler 25 Apr 1930), (1 letter:
  - L.T. More to NF 21 Mar 1929; 15 Jul 1929 9 Sep 1929)., (3 letters:
  - NF to L.T. More 28 Mar 1929, 4 Nov 1929, 10 Jan 1944)., (3 letters:
  - S. Spring to NF 17 Aug 1928; 18 Sep 1928; 28 Nov 1928; 11 Dec 1928; 6 Feb 1929; 18 Apr 1929; 20 Sep 1929; 2 Oct 1929; 8 Oct 1929; 9 Oct 1929; 11 Nov 1929; 6 Nov 1929; 21 Dec 1929; 31 Dec 1929; 4 Mar 1930; 6 May 1930)., (16 letters:
  - NF to S. Spring 3 Aug 1928; 26 Aug 1928; 25 Nov 1928; 4 Dec 1928; 22 Apr 1929; 11 Aug 1929; 23 Sep 1929; 25 Sep 1929; 5 Oct 1929; 18 Dec 1929; 24 Dec 1929; 3 May 1930)., (12 letters:
  - NF to Collector of Internal Revenue Apr 1929)., (1 letter
  - NF to J. Farrar 6 Jan 1930)., (1 letter:
  - A.R. Thompson to NF 17 Nov 1928; 9 Dec 1928; 24 Jan 1929; 8 Jul 1929; 2 Sep 1929; 29 Sep 1929; 29 Jan 1930; 12 Jan 1931.), (8 letters:
  - NF to A.R. Thompson 25 Nov 1928; 4 Jan 1929; 7 Aug 1929; 11 Sep 1929)., (4 letters:
  - #NF to S.P. Chase, Sept 24, 1929;comments on More's article which did not take T.S. Eliot seriously--he is a fellow contributor.
  - # NF to Louis More, Jan 10, 1944;on relationship between religion and humanism.
  - #Sam Spring to NF, August 17, 1928;will be glad to contribute. Tells what is doing to advance humanism in field of motion pictures and gives other views.
  - #Sam Spring to Dorothy Foerster, Sept 18, 1928;trying to get her diamonds for cheap.
  - #Spring to NF, Feb 6, 1929;legal particulars of [UNK] Carolina--laws upon royalties, copyrighted books...
  - #Spring to NF, Oct 8, 1929;implies that they were once roommates.
  - #Spring to NF, Oct 9, 1929;outline of attitude on which will write book (developing out of contribution to H & A.
  - #Spring to NF, Nov 6, 1929;new book will set up new philosophic attitude of Prevision--attempt to establish pragmatic, non-absolute, humanist standard of ourlook.
  - #Spring to NF, Dec 31, 1929;not bitter for being ejected from H & A.
  - #NF to Spring, Oct 5, 1929;really impressed with Spring's contribution, just reviewed, wants to place it at beginning of book.
  - #NF to Spring, Dec 18, 1929;breaks the news that [UNK] his article will not be in H & A.; tells him it is not because Sam is Jewish.
  - # NF to Spring, May 3, 1930;will accept dictatorship of U. of Iowa School of letters at $9000/year.
  - #Bernard Bandler II to NF, April 4, 1929;will contribute article on humanism and psychology--ctiticized psychologists for not giving definition of the normal.
  - #NF to Bandler, Sept 20, 1929;disappointed in article for H & A, please rewrite.
  - #NF to Bandler, Oct 14, 1929;new effort acceptable.
  - #Alan K. Thompson to NF, Nov 17, 1928;asks NF if he can contribute.
  - Correspondence: Clark & Warren
  - #Austin Warren to NF, April 24, 1929;from A.W., total of 3 letters
  - #H.H. Clark to NF, Dec 13, 1926(1st of series)
    Note: in this series, NF to Clark are interspersed.
  - #Clark to NF, Oct 5, 1928;thanking for opportunity to write in H & A.
  - #NF to Clark, Nov 26, 1928;needs someone to write [UNK] on psychology in H & A-- essential worth in Aristotle
  - #Clark, Nov 26, 1928,comments on NF's article on Freneau.
  - #Clark to NF, April 8, 1929,gives first lead to possibility of Sidney K. Gair (a nonacademic), for article in H & A.
  - #Jay B. Hubbell, managing ed., American Lit., to Clark, March 29, 1929,about Clark's review of NF's book being edited.
  - #Clark to NF, Aug 15, 1930,comment on NF's The Literary Historians, where exposed the fallacies of the doctrine of historic relativity.
  - #NF to Clark, Aug 24, 1930,last of series.
  - Miscellaneous loose items
  - #cards with quotes from Aristotle
  - #W.B. Cairns to NF, March 1, 1919.
  - Karl Young to G.R. Elliott, Oct 3, 1918,--NF's campaign for a more humanistic study of the humanities., total of 11 letters
  - #assorted notes and few loose letters and some article reprints.
  - These letters were not listed on main holding sheet, but were found in an unmarked folder in the middle of the collection. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - A. Warren to NF 24 Apr 1929,16th Sunday after Trinity [no year]; 7 Dec 1929), (3 letters:
    - H.H. Clark to NF 13 Dec 1926; 24 Apr 1927; 28 Oct 1927; 23 Aug 1928; 5 Oct 1928; 27 Oct 1928; 14 Nov 1928; 13 Dec 1928; 19 Dec 1928; 26 Dec 1928; 29 Dec 1928; 31 Dec 1928; 4 Jan 1928; 9 Jan 1929; 10 Jan 1929; 28 Jan 1929; 8 Apr 1929; 30 Mar 1929; 10 July 1929; 6 Sep 1929; 29 Sep 1929; 30 Oct 1929; 6 Nov 1929; 10 Nov 1929; undated; 7 Dec 1929; undated; 9 Jan 1930; 18 Jan 1930; 21 Feb 1930; 22 May 1930; 5 Apr 1930; 30 Apr 1930; 31 May 1930; 6 June 1930; 29 June 1930; 15 Aug 1930., (37 letters: